Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998), 1990-1991; 29 cassettes, 29 master compact discs, 29 access compact discs
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 26 November 1990, Nov 26, 1990; cuid36253; [00:00 - 10:00] More on attempts by Brehon Law Society to gain NGO status in U.N. O'Dwyer impressed that African and Indian countries were acutely aware of situation in Northern Ireland. Those countries were friendly to O'Dwyer's proposal
    Duration: 41 Minutes. Preservation note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 26 November 1990, Nov 26, 1990; cuid36254; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer's early experience with Hibernians. His stand against the condemnation of a member accused of communist leanings.Injustice of Doherty case - remains in jail now for over seven years. Influence of Thatcher on recent bail hearing.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 11, Track 2, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 11)
    [01:59] At this point he's been in jail for over seven years?
    [07:41] What do you think the reason is for that [Doherty not criticizing U.S.] ?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 December 1990, Dec 7, 1990; cuid36255; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer's view of Bar Association of the city of New York. Its hesitancy to admit women. His reasons for not joining. Formation of National Lawyer's Guild and bios of founding members Frank Walsh, Louis McCabe, and Ferdinand Pecora. [10:00 - 20:00] More on National Lawyers Guild. Founders, political position of the Guild, members. O'Dwyer became president of New York chapter in 1947. Government tactics during the McCarthy period. Difference in opinion between the Guild and the Civil Liberties Union regarding whether or not to defend Communists. [20:00 - end] Irish issues and their reception within the National Lawyers Guild. O'Dwyer's separation from older generations of Irish and Irish Americans, then the Catholic church over such issues as divorce laws. O'Dwyer left the Guild for a time over the issue of anti-Semitism by the Russian government.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 1, Cassette 12, Box 3, Cd 12, Track 1, Box 4)
    [08:30] May I ask you what a bucket shop is?
    [12:43] Did the Guild start in New York or in California?
    [13:11] What about the year that they started?
    [18:19] Did the Civil Liberties Union do anything for the Irish Community that you recall?
    [19:35] The National Lawyers Guild wasn't in existence then [1916-1922] of course. Where do they tie in to having an effect on the Irish community?So now we have subsequent members that are of Irish extraction and working for the Irish cause?
    [21:12] Mary Murphy, the lady that you referred to, what was her role at that time?
    Duration: 63 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 December 1990, Dec 7, 1990; cuid36256; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer explains history of anti-Semitism in Russia. While with the NLG, O'Dwyer's confrontation with the NLG over Russia's involvement in genocide and his estrangement from the organization. [10:00 - 20:00] Discussion of why Marxist theories were successful in Russia. More reasons why O'Dwyer was dissatisfied with the NLG.Civil rights in Ireland. NLG team sent to Northern Ireland to assess situation. Group of African American Protestant ministers who also went to Northern Ireland to promote non-violent means of resolving situation. [20:00 - end] Conclusion of NLG and minister group involvement in Northern Ireland conflict.Formation of Bohola Society and anecdote about antagonism between Canon Higgins and O'Dwyer family.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 1, Cassette 12, Box 3, Cd 12, Track 2, Box 4)
    [02:49] Was the National Guild involved in this situation?
    [08:48] Had he [Murray Gordon] already sent the letter in?
    [09:48] How long were you actually estranged from them?
    [20:00] Did you have a role in any of this? [either group going to N.I.]
    [21:50] Long after the film? And the visit? [NLG report from N.I.]
    [30:18] Which sister was this?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 December 1990, Dec 7, 1990; cuid36257; [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer's experiences with fundraising, beginning with his work to raise funds for new rafters for his church in Bohola to his later experiences with the United Jewish Appeal, the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies, and the Mayo Foundation for the Handicapped, which helped him to fund the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home. [10:00 - 20:00] More on origination of reforestation idea. Influence of Sean McBride. Contributions of O'Dwyer's nephew David Waters and Dr. Eoin McKiernan, who formed the Irish American Culture Institute. Option to buy 20-mile narrow strip of land from the railroad for project. [20:00 - end] Conclusion of reforestation project. Need for local support of project. Kinds of trees being planted, etc.O'Dwyer's beginnings in fundraising. More on United Jewish Appeal and its organizational structure. Being invited to speak on behalf of the organization. What he learned from his experiences with the organization.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 3, Cd 13, Track 1, Box 1, Cassette 13, Box 4)
    [09:48] Who conceived of that idea? [reforestation as an investment for the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home]
    [13:58] They were environmental corps [that David Waters runs] ?
    [18:03] How narrow a strip was it?
    [24:32] Who is left in charge in Ireland? You said you were going to use local people? Is there a committee formed locally?
    [30:34] About how old were you then?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 7 December 1990, Dec 7, 1990; cuid36258; [00:00 - 10:00] More on fundraising. How experience as a trial lawyer helped him deliver fundraising speeches. More on Federation for Jewish Philanthropies and its functions. O'Dwyer's inability to raise funds for his own campaigns. Becoming more confident with appeals for contributions as he gets older. Contributions of Jewish communities to New York City. [10:00 - 20:00] Experience at Fordham University as a pre-law student and not being accepted by Irish Americans because he was Irish-born. Contrasted with experience with a student study group at St. John's Law School. Discussed conversations and activities with the study group and what he learned from those experiences. [20:00 - end] Conclusion of thoughts on St. John's study group.Belief that the U.S. economy during the Depression created thinking people. Influence of Thomas Paine on O'Dwyer's thought process.Brief discussion of Oscar Bernstien and influence of his Jewish intellectual and artist friends.O'Dwyer's relationship with Irish community vs. Jewish community.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 13, Track 2, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 13)
    [04:57] Why to you think that is? [O'Dwyer's inability to raise funds for his own campaigns]
    [05:30] I can understand that feeling, but don't you think it's a little more? You said it's easy for you, or easier for you, to ask for funds for someone else. I think that's true of some of us. Do you think that would have to do with, just your whole life? Your defense of others?
    [09:42] What created the link between you and the Jewish community to begin with, do you remember? Was it because of your partnership with Oscar Bernstien?
    [15:25] Who was this? [The student who introduced O'Dwyer to study group]
    [19:23] Did you study only with Jewish students?
    [23:05] Is Tom Paine one of your favorite authors?
    [23:36] This is Oscar Bernstien?
    [26:30] How did all of these relationships that you developed over the years with the Jewish community have an effect on your relationship with the Irish community? How did they come together if and when they did?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 19 December 1990, Dec 19, 1990; cuid36259; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Irish-Jewish relations. Story of Irish Institute and how Jewish contributions helped found it, so O'Dwyer, to recognize that fact, later donated money from the Irish Institute to fund the completion of a book on the history of Irish Jews. Irish and Jewish communities historically having similar political views. Disapproval of many Jewish leaders of O'Dwyer's joining the American League for a Free Palestine. [10:00 - 20:00] Other political disagreements with Jewish community.Passing of McBride principles bill in Florida after Senator Weinstein introduced it. [20:00 - end] Contributions of Jewish politicians to Irish causes. Congressman Gary Ackerman's interest in Northern Ireland. Jewish politicians' help in the passing of the McBride principles in New York state.Sympathetic attitudes of Jews towards Great Britain.Begins story about relationship with Eric Newgarden, a German Jew who immigrated to New York.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 3, Cd 14, Track 1, Box 1, Cassette 14, Box 4)
    [18:00] Why do you think that he [Senator Weinstein] went out for it [McBride bill] ?
    Duration: 61 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 19 December 1990, Dec 19, 1990; cuid36260; [00:00 - 10:00] Life of Eric Newgarden. Life in and escape from Germany.Irish Jews. Effects of immigration, fundraising efforts for new Jewish nursing home in Dublin.Beginning of story about visit with Gary Ackerman to synagogue in Belfast. [10:00 - 20:00] Jewish community in Belfast, Jewish prosecutor in diplock court.Discussion of Bishop's Committee for Irish Immigration, an organization that concentrated on helping prisoners overseas, especially in Britain, and Irish tinkers/travelers, nomadic people indigenous to Ireland. Description and history of travelers. [20:00 - end] Conclusion of traveler discussion - their education, struggle for rights.Sean McCarthy bio. Drawing up his will to distribute $100,000 he had accumulated during his life.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 1, Cassette 14, Box 4, Cd 14, Track 2, Box 3)
    [09:14] They are going to build this house in Cork City?
    [10:41] In Belfast? Is there only one [synagogue] ?
    [13:58] This Jewish prosecutor - did you find out, was he brought into Belfast or was he originally from there?
    [21:55] Would you call them a type of gypsy?
    [22:29] Where did they originally come from?
    [24:25] Because they lived by moving around and they just learned from their way of life, or were they formally educated?
    [25:34] They're called travelers today?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 05 March 1991, Mar 5, 1991; cuid36261; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Sean McCarthy. Death, dissemination of money to family, civil rights organizations and activists, and to indigenous groups. [10:00 - 20:00] O'Dwyer's attempts for travelers to become a non-governmental organization with the U.N.John Danis, Jewish friend of O'Dwyer's son Bill, and his founding of an organization to hold fundraisers for Cork University.Plans to buy more acreage to fund O'Dwyer-Cheshire home in the future. [20:00 - end] Description of O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation to fund the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home in the future. Contribution by Tom Laffey (one of the Fort Worth Five), Frank Moran, and David Waters.Mary Robinson, president of Ireland. Background (education, work as a lawyer and senator), plans to meet with her on last trip to Ireland. **discussion cut off**O'Dwyer's review of a book by Fergus Finley, campaign manager for Robinson, for the Irish Voice.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 15, Track 1, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 15)
    [11:58] The indigenous group - the travelers - are they known for committing crimes throughout Ireland?
    Duration: 27 minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background; Side 2 is blank.
  - Paul O'Dwyer -1 April 1991, Apr 1, 1991; cuid36262; [00:00 - 10:00] Celebration of Irish Heritage Day at Gracie Mansion. The mayor asked O'Dwyer to address the guests. When asked how he plans to deal with British as commissioner at U.N., O'Dwyer responded that he would treat them just like everyone else. He then tells of an encounter/confrontation with Ambassador Hanay from Great Britain. [10:00 - 20:00] Speaking at Catholic Universities while running for Senator. Gustin L. Reichvack and his difficulty passing the bar. [20:00 - end] Conclusion of Gustin Reichvach discussion. O'Dwyer and others' help in convincing bar committee to pass him. O'Dwyer's speaking on his behalf when inducted as judge of the civil court in Brooklyn.Case about conservative tv/radio personality being charged with evasion of state income taxes. Prosecuted instead of fined because personality had offended so many people with his criticism of liberal democrats.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 1, Cassette 16, Box 4, Cd 16, Track 1, Box 3)
    [07:17] This is ambassador who? From?
    [09:05] What date was this?
    [10:19] This was related to the [Desmond] Ellis incident?
    [12:01] Do you recall, who else was at this meeting besides the mayor and yourself?
    [12:17] Now when you spoke, you spoke and addressed the whole 350 so they all heard this discussion?
    [12:27] Press meaning who [was in attendance at the mayor's gathering] ?
    [12:47] Was the New York Times represented?
    [16:13] You considered yourself…you're talking about 'we.' What do you mean by 'we?'
    [24:57] They [bar committee] held him [Gustin Reichvach] a year before admitting him?
    [25:03] What made them turn around?
    Duration: 38 minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer -1 April 1991, Apr 1, 1991; cuid36263; [00:00 - end] Conclusion of tax evasion case. More on tv/radio personality's opinions, polling the jury at the trial, change of verdict.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 16, Track 2, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 16)
    [00:50] Abe Bergis or this other fellow [was a supporter of the IRA] ?
    [01:00] Was he Irish? This was a Jewish man who was a strong defender of the IRA?
    [03:08] When you poll the jury - can you explain exactly how you do that?
    [05:06] What made you poll the jury in this instance?
    [06:06] What was Judge Reichvach's affiliation with the Irish community if he had any?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 3 April 1991, Apr 3, 1991; cuid36264; [00:00 - 10:00] St. Patrick's Day Parade. Nomination of Joe Doherty as honorary grand marshal of the parade in New York. Committee also turned down the applications of groups including a gay and lesbian organization and the Brehon Law Society to march in the parade. Reasons for denial of application. Repercussions of denial of gay and lesbian organization for the mayor. [10:00 - 20:00] More on St. Patrick's Day Parade. Mayor's involvement in parade. Attempts to include all groups in parade. Gay and lesbian organization marching with Division 7 and the mayor's decision to walk in front of group. Conflict during parade. Fears of parade permit being taken away because of discriminatory practices of committee. [20:00 - end] More on St. Patrick's Day Parade. Fear of elimination of parade committee because of discriminatory practices. Public's reaction to parade. Nominations of Dorothy Hayden and Mary Holt Moore for grand marshals of parade.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 17, Track 1, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 17)
    [02:02] Why did they [parade committee] think you were out of order specifically?
    [04:36] They also were not allowed to march?
    [07:17] Imported for the occasion do you mean, or you're just stating that they're immigrants.
    [10:15] So what you were trying to do was prevent this from happening?
    [10:21] Does the mayor's office always hire the same St. Patrick's Day committee?
    [10:54] And the mayor always marches in the parade. Isn't that a fact?
    [12:43] About how much of an extension would that have amount to, an hour, two hours?
    [16:15] They accepted exactly what? That the mayor would walk in front of them, that there would be no sign indicating who they were, but everybody would know because the mayor had made mention that he would do this?
    [17:10] Who was the grand marshal this year?
    [17:24] And how far back was Division 7?
    [17:33] And how many hours was the whole parade?
    [18:] With the other 39 of the 40 units?
    Duration: 62 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 3 April 1991, Apr 3, 1991; cuid36265; [00:00 - end] Begins story of the Mellon Foundation showing exactly where the first Melon left from Ireland to establish himself in U.S. Recreated home of Archbishop Hughes.More on Hughes and situation of Irish Americans before the Civil War. Matriarchal society, proselytizing to Irish American children in school, origination of parochial schools. Anti-Catholic sentiment throughout U.S. history. Development of Irish American identity.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 3, Cd 18, Track 1, Box 2, Cassette 18, Box 4)
    [00:18] Where was the village?
    [10:19] Do you think that education system had a lot to do with giving Irish Americans identity?
    Duration: 12 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background; Side 2 is blank.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 4 April 1991, Apr 4, 1991; cuid36266; [00:00 - 10:00] Irish American leaders' attempts to work through Washington to solve Northern Ireland problems. Hostility from State Department. Ted Kennedy's contributions to the work. Prime Minister Lynch of the Irish Republic and his influence over American politicians to favor Britain. Formation of Ad Hoc Committee in Congress under Mario Biaggi. Establishment's prosecution of Biaggi. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Biaggi's prosecution and life.Role of Speaker of the House of Representatives.Daniel Patrick Moynihan. Life. Success in winning support of Jewish population. Books about ethnicities in New York. Protest by O'Dwyer and other Irish Americans over Thatcher's visit to address joint session of Congress and Moynihan's actions. [20:00 - end ] More on Moynihan. Use of his book Beyond the Melting Pot in universities. His interference with O'Dwyer's attempts to incorporate the Northern Ireland question into the Democratic National Convention when O'Dwyer was delegated to represent Jesse Jackson the first time he ran.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 2, Cassette 19, Box 4, Cd 19, Track 1, Box 3)
    [19:16] This was the chairman of the House of Representatives?
    [20:14] Was this the book called Beyond the Melting Pot?
    [20:28] It's used to teach in colleges. It's very widely read.
    Duration: 25 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background; Side 2 is blank.
  - Paul O'Dwyer -11 April 1991, Apr 11, 1991; cuid36267; [00:00 - 10:00] History of Gaelic Athletic Association in Ireland and America. History of Irish American Athletic Club. Accomplishments, buying and selling of Celtic Park. Dissolution of IAAC. GAA buying wooden stands from Celtic Park. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Athletics. Effects of Depression on athletic clubs' membership. Description of Gaelic Games - history of playing pitch, turnout at games during Depression, teams, need for players, O'Dwyer's involvement in athletics. [20:00 - end (31)] More on Athletics. Effect of end of World War II on Games. End of Argentinean hurling game. Duffy, real estate agent for the Department of Transportation and his attempts to rid the city of 'surplus' property, including the field where the Gaelic Games were held. Manhattan College's interest in purchasing field. O'Dwyer called in to prevent city from selling the field.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 4, Cd 20, Track 1, Box 3, Box 2, Cassette 20)
    [04:24] In what particular sport [did Martin Sheridan compete] ?
    [15:07] So they lost their formal structure, so to speak, but they still maintained their social status?
    [15:29] When there was pride how many [attended the Gaelic Games] ?
    [15:39] Do you recall how many teams there were?
    [21:29] Was there ever any international competition between Argentina and the U.S. or New York and Ireland?
    Duration: 43 Minutes. Preservation Note: "Buzzing" heard in background.
  - Paul O'Dwyer -11 April 1991, Apr 11, 1991; cuid36268; [ - end] How many teams do you have left now?; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 3, Cd 20, Track 2, Box 4, Box 2, Cassette 20)
    [00:00] More on Athletics. O'Dwyer's argument to Col. Sydney Bingham, head of transit system for New York City, to save field. Bingham's intervention and saving the land. By 1990/1991, the city again wanted to sell the land and Manhattan College was still interested. Change in attitudes of leaders of Gaelic Athletic Association since the 1940s and 1950s.19 April 1991Update on situation. Meeting on 17 April to sell land to Manhattan College. Conflict between parties over the issue of when lockers and shower rooms would be constructed by the O'Donnells. Resolution of conflict.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 April 1991, Apr 17, 1991; cuid36269; [00:00 - 10:00] History of Irish American newspapers. Irish World and Industrial Liberator and Patrick Ford, the paper's founder. Irish Advocate and its founder, John C. O'Connor. Irish immigrants being influenced to become Democrats as soon as they arrive. [10:00 - 20:00] More on newspapers. Continues with Irish Advocate and more on John C. O'Connor. John C.'s grandson Carroll O'Connor and his work as an actor. Gaelic American. History and catering to Clan na Gael news. Description of Clan na Gael organization. [20:00 - end] More on newspapers. Gaelic American - Palace Fund, Charles Rice, merger with Irish World.Labor unions. O'Dwyer's first joining a union. His experiences working on the waterfront in 1926.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 2, Cassette 21, Box 3, Cd 21, Track 1, Box 4)
    [01:58] Was this throughout Ireland or were the head schools mainly in the West?
    [03:42] Was this a newspaper for New Yorkers primarily?
    [04:21] Was there a large Irish community in Utah?
    [16:39] About how long was that paper in existence? Do you recall around the time it started?
    [18:25] Was the Clan na Gael established here or in Ireland?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 April 1991, Apr 17, 1991; cuid36270; [00:00 - 10:00] More on labor unions. Ethnicities of various unions. Leaders, such as Joe Ryan, Dan Tobin, William Greene. Effects of passage of Wagner Act in the 1930s. Auto Workers Union and United Miners Union. [10:00 - 20:00] More on labor unions. Molly Maguires. History, aims. Irish American rail workers. Assorted labor stories. [20:00 - end] More on labor unions. Labor unrest during Works Progress Administration. Communist organizers and members in unions. Description of Michael Quill, labor leader. O'Dwyer's experiences with Quill and help in his campaign for City Council. Amalgamation of New York Central and Pennsylvania railroad line.; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc (Box 2, Cassette 21, Box 3, Cd 21, Track 2, Box 4)
    [21:02] Why is that [that Communists were the best organizers] ?
    [26:59] What was your affiliation at this time with Michael Quill and the railroad union?